<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>dmmme</title><description>dmmme</description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/news-and-events</link><item><title>UP DMMME Faculty awarded with the Ian Morley Prize by the University of Queensland</title><description><![CDATA[         UP DMMME faculty member, Assistant Professor Djoan Kate T. Tungpalan, was recently awarded with the Ian Morley Prize by the Julius Kruttschnitt Minerals Research Center (JKMRC) of the University of Queensland for her overall excellent performance in her dissertation study entitled "Development of a novel methodology for flowsheet design and evaluation in prefeasibility/feasibility projects" and her contributions to the overall cultural life of the mining and minerals engineering<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_22bf96b4fde349b0a1c63401f57e1792.png"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2015/03/09/UP-DMMME-Faculty-awarded-with-the-Ian-Morley-Prize-by-the-University-of-Queensland</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2015/03/09/UP-DMMME-Faculty-awarded-with-the-Ian-Morley-Prize-by-the-University-of-Queensland</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 07:02:24 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>       UP DMMME faculty member, Assistant Professor Djoan Kate T. Tungpalan, was recently awarded with the Ian Morley Prize by the Julius Kruttschnitt Minerals Research Center (JKMRC) of the University of Queensland for her overall excellent performance in her dissertation study entitled &quot;Development of a novel methodology for flowsheet design and evaluation in prefeasibility/feasibility projects&quot; and her contributions to the overall cultural life of the mining and minerals engineering community.</div><div>Assistant Professor Djoan Kate T. Tungpalan (rightmost) receiving the Ian Morley Shield from no less than the children of Mr. Ian Morley whose photo is shown in the background.</div><div>       Despite her very busy research schedule, Prof. Tungpalan still had time to serve as head of the student body organization at the JKMRC and the organization of Filipino-Australian students in UQ.  Apart from that, she has been involved in a project called &quot;Designer Tailings&quot;, which is a collaborative project among the different centers of the Sustainable Mining Institute (SMI) of UQ.  She is also involved in collaborative projects of UQ with the Mining Consortium of the Philippines currently composed of some of the universities offering Mining Education namely, University of the Philippines-Diliman, Mindanao Institute of Technology-Iligan and General Santos campuses, and the University of Southeastern Philippines.</div><div>This prestigious award essentially immortalized Prof. Tungpalan as her name is now written on the Ian Morley Shield, together with the other winners in the past 25 years.  In the history of this award, Professor Tungpalan is only the 4th woman awardee apart from being the silver jubilee awardee, which made it more special.</div><div>The Ian Morley Prize was established in honor of the contributions of Mr. Ian Morley to the growth and development of the mining industry in Australia including his contributions to the mining education, primarily through his works at the University of Queensland.</div><div>Professor Tungpalan is currently completing her research work at the University of Queensland under the supervision of Dr. Luke Keeney, Dr. Elaine Wightman, and most especially, Prof. Emmy Manlapig, who is also an esteemed alumnus of the UP Metallurgical Engineering Program and the 2014 UPAE Professional Awardee for Engineering Education. </div><div> Assistant Professor Djoan Kate T. Tungpalan (third from right) with the JKMRC Board of Trustees (on her right) and the children of Mr. Ian Morely (on her left).Assistant Professor Djoan Kate T. Tungpalan (third from right) with the JKMRC Board of Trustees (on her right) and the children of Mr. Ian Morely (on her left).</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>UP Grad tops 2014 Metallurgical Engineering board exam; UP is top performing school</title><description><![CDATA[Terence Lucero F. Menor, magna cum laude graduate of DMMME, leads the 38 passers of the 2014 Metallurgical Engineering board exam with his 88.20% rating. Six other DMMME graduates placed in the top 10 namely, Jan Remyr A. Astillera (Rank 2), April Joy H. Garete (Rank 4), Geoffrey Ray L. Nablo (Rank 4), Florian D.C. Servidad (Rank 5), Emmanuel L. Ballad, Jr. (Rank 6), and Jonathan Arnold Q. Natarte (Rank 10). University of the Philippines Diliman is also the top performing school having 95.45%<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_d9955749ea3f493fa8954d974b56a701.png"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/10/18/UP-Grad-tops-2014-Metallurgical-Engineering-board-exam-UP-is-top-performing-school</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/10/18/UP-Grad-tops-2014-Metallurgical-Engineering-board-exam-UP-is-top-performing-school</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 14:50:39 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Terence Lucero F. Menor, magna cum laude graduate of DMMME, leads the 38 passers of the 2014 Metallurgical Engineering board exam with his 88.20% rating. Six other DMMME graduates placed in the top 10 namely, Jan Remyr A. Astillera (Rank 2), April Joy H. Garete (Rank 4), Geoffrey Ray L. Nablo (Rank 4), Florian D.C. Servidad (Rank 5), Emmanuel L. Ballad, Jr. (Rank 6), and Jonathan Arnold Q. Natarte (Rank 10).</div><div>University of the Philippines Diliman is also the top performing school having 95.45% passing rate. Below is a complete list of the new Metallurgical Engineers from UP DMMME:</div><div> AGCAOILI, APOLLO RILLONASTILLERA, JAN REMYR ACOSTABALLAD, EMMANUEL JR LEGASPIBONDAD, CHEASSYLYNNE BALTAZARCAHIG, AVA PEARL APARICICATALUÑA, RISA MAR SANTESCIRIACO, LUISA ANGELI REYESCONQUILLA, RAFAEL LOPEZGARCIA, EUNICE MAIRE DIAZGARETE, APRIL JOY HAPITANGRANDE, ARCEE SARDIÑOLAMENOR, TERENCE LUCERO FERNANDEZNABLO, GEOFFREY RAY LAVISTENATARTE, JONATHAN ARNOLD QUINTANAOMAGA, GILLIAN NIKKA MANDINGRAMOS, JEAN LOUISE PANGANREGIDOR, HANNA CZARISE EUGENIOSANTOS, STEPHANIE LIMCOLIOCSERVIDAD, FLORIAN DELA CRUZTABELL, VICTOR OLIVER LUMAINVASQUEZ, MARK EDWARD ROMERO</div><div>The Metallurgical Engineering board examiners were Engr. Agustin M. Fudolig (Chairman) and Engr. Juancho Pablo S. Calvez (Member).</div><div>The oathtaking ceremonies were held last October 4 at Macapagal Ancestral Homes, Timoga, Iligan City and last October 10 at Club Filipino, Greenhills, San Juan, Metro Manila.</div><div>Mabuhay ang mga bagong Inhenyero ng Bayan!</div><div>Source:</div><div>http://www.prc.gov.ph</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME Student Wins Best Presenter in Malaysia Conference</title><description><![CDATA[  September 5, 2014 - DMMME MS MSE student, Michael R. Tan was awarded as the Best Presenter at the 2014 3rd International Conference on Engineering and Innovative Materials held at Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia for the paper entitled "Electroless Deposition of Copper Nanostructures in Aqueous Solution". Undergraduate students from the Sustainable Electronic Materials Laboratory, Lance de Jesus, Kathy Lois Amores, and Ellaine Datu also contributed to the project which is being led by Dr. Mary<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_084999c1af1b4940926d2944d491fc71.png"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/10/15/DMMME-Student-Wins-Best-Presenter-in-Malaysia-Conference</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/10/15/DMMME-Student-Wins-Best-Presenter-in-Malaysia-Conference</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 03:55:48 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>September 5, 2014 - DMMME MS MSE student, Michael R. Tan was awarded as the Best Presenter at the 2014 3rd International Conference on Engineering and Innovative Materials held at Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia for the paper entitled &quot;Electroless Deposition of Copper Nanostructures in Aqueous Solution&quot;. Undergraduate students from the Sustainable Electronic Materials Laboratory, Lance de Jesus, Kathy Lois Amores, and Ellaine Datu also contributed to the project which is being led by Dr. Mary Donnabelle L. Balela.</div><div>Two other DMMME graduate students were invited to present their papers as well. Christian Mark Pelicano presented his study entitled &quot;Growth of Zinc Oxide Nanostructures from Zinc foil&quot; while Nathan de Guzman and Aurelia Mechilina presented the study &quot;Electroless Deposition of Silver Nanoparticles and Nanowires in Ethylene Glycol&quot;. The studies will be published in Advanced Materials Research Journal (ISSN: 1022-6680) as a special issue.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME Participates in the 1st IMEP Conference</title><description><![CDATA[Faculty members and students of the Department of Mining, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering (DMMME) participated in the first Institute of Materials Engineers of the Philippines (IMEP) Conference with the theme “Advancing Technologies in the Philippines through Materials Science and Engineering Education, Research, and Practice”, successfully held last 31 July 2014 at the Eastwood Richmonde Hotel in Quezon City. Participants of the 1st IMEP Conference   The keynote address was delivered by<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_d38be765870941cf930be23516eaa5b5.jpg"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/05/DMMME-Participates-in-the-1st-IMEP-Conference</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/05/DMMME-Participates-in-the-1st-IMEP-Conference</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 03:11:21 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Faculty members and students of the Department of Mining, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering (DMMME) participated in the first Institute of Materials Engineers of the Philippines (IMEP) Conference with the theme “Advancing Technologies in the Philippines through Materials Science and Engineering Education, Research, and Practice”, successfully held last 31 July 2014 at the Eastwood Richmonde Hotel in Quezon City.</div><div>Participants of the 1st IMEP Conference</div><div>The keynote address was delivered by the Undersecretary for Research and Development of the Department of Science and Technology Dr. Amelia P. Guevara. Visiting professors from Japan, namely Prof. Hisao Yanagi and Prof. Michiya Fujiki of the Nara Institute of Science and Technology also shared their expertise in materials engineering research. Moreover, a number of faculty members from DMMME, including Dr. Magdaleno R. Vasquez, Jr., Dr. Manolo G. Mena, Dr. Alberto V. Amorsolo, Jr., and Dr. Leslie Joy L. Diaz, have also been invited speakers in the said conference.</div><div>The paper entitled Production of Amorphous and Crystalline Silica from Philippine Waste Rice Hull of Ms. Emie S. Mirasol and Dr. Rinlee Butch M. Cervera from DMMME bagged the Best Poster Award.</div><div>Dr. Manolo G. Mena during his presentation entitled: </div><div>“Semiconductor Packaging- Living in a Material World”</div><div>About IMEP [1]</div><div>The Institute of Materials Engineers of the Philippines, also known as IMEP, traces its humble beginnings when the twelve incorporators assembled with the intention of strengthening and further promoting the materials engineering field through the formation of a professional society. As the only organization of its kind in the country, IMEP aims to actively engage in education, practice, and dissemination of technical information in the field of materials engineering through its cooperation with government and private institutions.</div><div>In May 31, 2013, IMEP was recognized by the Securities and Exchange Commission as a non-stock, non-profit organization. The first general assembly, attended by 59 founding members, was held in July 6, 2013 at the DMMME of the University of the Philippines in Diliman (UP Diliman) Quezon City. It was in the same day that the first Board of Directors was elected. The oath taking took place in Nov. 23, 2013 during the 1st IMEP Annual Meeting (iMEET), which was held at the University Hotel, UP Diliman. During the iMEET, the official logo created by Ms. Catherine Kaye Garrido was also launched.</div><div>For more information about IMEP, you may visit www.imep-org.inc or email your queries to imep.inc@gmail.com.</div><div>[1] Cruz, John Kenneth A. 2014. History of IMEP. IMEP 2014 Conference Proceedings.</div><div>Photographs © Myra Ruth Poblete and Karlo Leandro Baladad</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>100% Passing Rate for UP Mining Engineering Graduates!</title><description><![CDATA[  The University of the Philippines Diliman is among the top performing schools in the recently concluded Mining Engineering Board Examination, garnering a 100% passing rate, of which seven graduates landed in the Top 10.   Prince Joseph Erneszer A. Javier, who graduated summa cum laude from the Department of Mining, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering (DMMME), leads the batch with an 89.6% rating. Close behind are Paola Grace D. Tuyor (Rank 2, 87.65%) and Mario Nikko A. Priela (Rank 3,<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_fec173f7d89e4f27a10db59a3eb2bbbb.png"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/100-Passing-Rate-for-UP-Mining-Engineering-Graduates</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/100-Passing-Rate-for-UP-Mining-Engineering-Graduates</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 09:09:47 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>The University of the Philippines Diliman is among the top performing schools in the recently concluded Mining Engineering Board Examination, garnering a 100% passing rate, of which seven graduates landed in the Top 10.</div><div>Prince Joseph Erneszer A. Javier, who graduated summa cum laude from the Department of Mining, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering (DMMME), leads the batch with an 89.6% rating. Close behind are Paola Grace D. Tuyor (Rank 2, 87.65%) and Mario Nikko A. Priela (Rank 3, 87%). Also in the Top 10 are DMMME graduates Gandalf D.S. Gutierrez (Rank 4), Jan Jeremiah V. Villaroman (Rank 7), Jes Francis M. Tanchuling (Rank 8), and Mark Anthony C. Perez (Rank 9).</div><div>Below is a complete list of the new Mining Engineers who graduated from the UP DMMME:</div><div>Alberto, Krizia Ann P.Amorin, Carlo DL.Castro, Robert Ben.Dela Cruz, Marc Francis A.Dimayuga, Harold Lester M.Fajura, Alen Kaye B.Feria, Rosanna Paola I.Gutierrez, Gandalf DS.Hernandez, Lia S.Javier, Prince Joseph Erneszer A.Langcay, Mae Lean I.Lopez, Daryl Philip T.Lumabao, Sara Gennedie C.Magalona, Ma. Abegail D.Maramba, Rializza T.Mondelo, Raian C.Perez, Mark Anthony C.Priela, Mario Nikko A.Tanchuling, Jes Francis M.Tuyor, Paola Grace D.Umerez, Christian Philip E.Vidal, Kenneth R.Villaroman, Jan Jeremiah V.</div><div>The Mining Engineering Licensure Examination was held last August 26-28, 2014 with Mr. Cornelio Q. Casido (Chairman), Mr. Rufino B. Bomasang, and Mr. Augusto C. Villaluna as examiners. A total of 123 out of 146 passed the examination.</div><div>Mabuhay ang mga bagong Inhenyero ng Bayan!</div><div>Source:</div><div>www.prc.gov.ph</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME in ERDT Congress 2014</title><description><![CDATA[DMMME faculty members and graduate students led by Dr. Magdaleno R. Vasquez, Jr., Chairman of the Department, participated in the ERDT Congress 2014 held on 25 July 2014 at the SMX Convention Center with the theme "Science and Technology for Disaster Preparedness and Resiliency."      Disasters, particularly typhoon, with its associated events like flooding and storm surge, and earthquake were highlighted in the Congress. Technologies that provided understanding and various means to predict and<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_dc3bccdd438a4ef58e1d8fcd876b231d.jpg"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/DMMME-in-ERDT-Congress-2014</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/DMMME-in-ERDT-Congress-2014</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 01:48:55 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>DMMME faculty members and graduate students led by Dr. Magdaleno R. Vasquez, Jr., Chairman of the Department, participated in the ERDT Congress 2014 held on 25 July 2014 at the SMX Convention Center with the theme &quot;Science and Technology for Disaster Preparedness and Resiliency.&quot;   </div><div>Disasters, particularly typhoon, with its associated events like flooding and storm surge, and earthquake were highlighted in the Congress. Technologies that provided understanding and various means to predict and address these disasters were presented by experts from the College of Engineering of UP Diliman and UP Los Banos, UP College of Social Work and Community Development, UP Marine Science Institute, University of Twente, PhilVolcs, the Local Government of Albay, and the Climate Change Commission.</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_dc3bccdd438a4ef58e1d8fcd876b231d.jpg"/><div>DMMME faculty and graduate students</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_738127908f104303b494e30bb5e70ff4.jpg"/><div>Poster entry on chitin extraction from shells of indigenous crab specie  </div><div>by Lorenz Anthony T. Fernando with his adviser, Dr. Leslie Joy L. Diaz</div><div>Poster presentations were also conducted by ERDT scholars including Mr. Lorenz Anthony T. Fernando, a graduate student from the Department pursuing a Master of Science degree in Materials Science and Engineering and a member of the Composite Materials Research Laboratory.</div><div>The Congress was attended by more than 600 participants from the industry, government, and academe, especially the member-universities of the ERDT Consortium.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME Garners Nine Awards at the 2014 MICROSPHIL Conference</title><description><![CDATA[The Department of Mining, Metallurgical, and Materials Engineering (DMMME) garnered nine awards during the annual scientific conference and general membership meeting of the Philippine Institute of Microscopists, Inc. (MICROSPHIL)  held last August 1-2, 2014 at the Advanced Device and Materials Testing Laboratory (ADMATEL), DOST Compound, Bicutan, Taguig City. The conference, with the theme, “Microscopy: A Tool for Advanced Materials Characterization and Failure Analysis,” featured presentation<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_ed0cd723fc2f4fb5aa4deaed1bbf7504.jpg"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/DMMME-Garners-Nine-Awards-at-the-2014-MICROSPHIL-Conference</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/09/04/DMMME-Garners-Nine-Awards-at-the-2014-MICROSPHIL-Conference</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 01:06:25 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>The Department of Mining, Metallurgical, and Materials Engineering (DMMME) garnered nine awards during the annual scientific conference and general membership meeting of the Philippine Institute of Microscopists, Inc. (MICROSPHIL)  held last August 1-2, 2014 at the Advanced Device and Materials Testing Laboratory (ADMATEL), DOST Compound, Bicutan, Taguig City. The conference, with the theme, “Microscopy: A Tool for Advanced Materials Characterization and Failure Analysis,” featured presentation of technical papers, workshops as well as posters and photomicrographs exhibits. </div><div>Researchers of Sustainable Electronic Materials with</div><div>one of the judges, Dr. Meliton Ordillas</div><div>Seven out of the nine awards of the department came from researchers of the Sustainable Electronic Materials (SEM) Project, headed by Dr. Mary Donnabelle L. Balela. The complete list of awards received by the department is shown below:</div><div>AWARDS</div><div>Best Oral Presentation (Physical Sciences)</div><div>1st Place - “Analysis of Dendrite Images Formed by Electrochemical Migration in a Semiconductor Sensor”</div><div>Junio, Jonathan; Belandres, Leo; Manolo, Mena G.</div><div>2nd Place - “Large Scale Synthesis of Copper Nanowires in Aqueous Solution&quot;</div><div>Felizco, Jenichi  Clairvaux E.; Magdaluyo, Eduardo, R.; Delmo, Michael P.; Balela, Mary Donnnabelle L.</div><div>3rd Place - “Synthesis of Nickel Nanowires under a Magnetic Field”</div><div>Rito, Thaddea Sheena O.; Balela, Mary Donnnabelle L.</div><div>Best Oral Presentation (Biological Sciences)</div><div>3rd Place – “Demineralization Kinetics Study of Chitin Extraction from Shells of Philippine Blue Swimming Crab (Portunus Pelagicus)”</div><div>Ongkiko, Aileen Grace M.; Vasquez, Jasmine Z.; Diaz, Leslie Joy L.</div><div>Best Poster Presentation</div><div>3<div>rd Place - “Characterization of Silver Nanowires Synthesized via Self-Seeding Polyol Method”</div></div><div>De Guzman, Nathaniel T.; Mechilina, Aurelia C.; Balela, Mary Donnnabelle L. </div><div>Best Micrographs</div><div>MICROSPHIL was co-founded by former DMMME Chairman, Dr. Meliton U. Ordillas, Jr. It is a non-stock, non-profit professional organization recognized by the Securities and Exchange Commission since July 2001 with its certificate of incorporation awarded on September of the same year.  One of the various activities of the society is organizing conferences and trainings, including the 5th ASEAN Microscopy Conference held in November 2005.  </div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Innovating through Entrepreneurship: The PhilDev IDEA Global Entrepreneurship Workshop Series 2014</title><description><![CDATA[Six DMMME faculty members participated in the second and final leg of the IDEA Global Entrepreneurship Workshop Series last July 25-27, 2014 at the Asian Institute of Management, Makati. Three out of the six faculty members, namely, Astrid Ayla Liberato, Eduardo Magdaluyo, Jr., and Jill Manapat, have successfully completed the entire workshop series by attending the first leg last March 14-15, 2014 in the same venue.   Some of UP College of Engineering's faculty members and researchers with one<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_bf19bfbf3b964a1d92f5404fbce9f960.jpg"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/29/Innovating-through-Entrepreneurship-The-PhilDev-IDEA-Global-Entrepreneurship-Workshop-Series-2014</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/29/Innovating-through-Entrepreneurship-The-PhilDev-IDEA-Global-Entrepreneurship-Workshop-Series-2014</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 05:56:27 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Six DMMME faculty members participated in the second and final leg of the IDEA Global Entrepreneurship Workshop Series last July 25-27, 2014 at the Asian Institute of Management, Makati. Three out of the six faculty members, namely, Astrid Ayla Liberato, Eduardo Magdaluyo, Jr., and Jill Manapat, have successfully completed the entire workshop series by attending the first leg last March 14-15, 2014 in the same venue.</div><div>Some of UP College of Engineering's faculty members and researchers with one of IDEA workshop's facilitators, Mr. Eros Resmini (Photo credit: AAELiberato)</div><div>IDEA, which stands for Innovative Development for Entrepreneurship Advancement, is a three-year program pioneered by the Philippine S&amp;T Development Foundation (PhilDev S&amp;T) that aims “to create a sustainable entrepreneurial ecosystem in the Philippines [1].” Some of the projects under the said program include the workshop series and an annual symposium, the first of which was also attended by DMMME faculty members and researchers last March 17, 2014 at the Edsa Shangri-La Hotel.</div><div>The facilitators of the workshop series were Ahmet Alpdemir and Eros Resmini, both experienced entrepreneurs from Silicon Valley. Seven topics were discussed as follows: market demand, strategic planning and modeling, customer validation, competitive analysis, sound execution plan, company building, and solid financial support. A talk on intellectual property practice in the Philippines was also conducted by Atty. Peter Calimag who served as the Assistant Secretary for Revenue Operations &amp; Legal Affairs from 2010-2012 at the Department of Finance. Participants of the workshop included start-up entrepreneurs, educators, students, and industry representatives among others.</div><div>DMMME is committed in promoting an entrepreneurial spirit among its faculty and students in order to ensure that research projects are translated into products and services that are useful to society. As proof of this commitment, curricular changes are on-going for all DMMME programs in order to introduce a design research track as well as entrepreneurship into the curriculum. </div><div>[1] http://phildev.org/wp/idea/</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME Attends Electrochemistry Workshop</title><description><![CDATA[Faculty members and researchers from DMMME attended the one-day Metrohm Autolab Electrochemistry Day organized by Dynalab Corporation last July 7, 2014 at the De La Salle University, Manila. The speaker, Mr. Luca Pini, discussed the basics of electrochemistry, impedance spectroscopy, and instrumentation, specifically on how to use the potentiostat/galvanostat for different applications in electrodeposition, corrosion, energy, and environmental electrochemistry among other topics.   DMMME faculty<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/e0b8ad_ee595020ea1d4707b95b969479c290b9.jpg"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/29/DMMME-Attends-Electrochemistry-Workshop</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/29/DMMME-Attends-Electrochemistry-Workshop</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Faculty members and researchers from DMMME attended the one-day Metrohm Autolab Electrochemistry Day organized by Dynalab Corporation last July 7, 2014 at the De La Salle University, Manila. The speaker, Mr. Luca Pini, discussed the basics of electrochemistry, impedance spectroscopy, and instrumentation, specifically on how to use the potentiostat/galvanostat for different applications in electrodeposition, corrosion, energy, and environmental electrochemistry among other topics.</div><div>DMMME faculty members and researchers with Mr. Luca Pini (Photo credit: AAELiberato)</div><div>DMMME currently has a Metrohm Autolab potentiostat/galvanostat in its Smart and Functional Materials Laboratory. The said equipment is being used for studies involving batteries, solid polymer electrolytes, soil purification, and other related research projects.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DMMME Roadshow: Ilocos Sur Leg</title><description><![CDATA[The DMMME Publicity Committee members (Mr. Audric Zuriel Cruz, Mr. John Kenneth Cruz, and Ms. Jill Manapat) went to different schools in Ilocos Sur last June 26-27, 2014 to introduce and promote the mining, metallurgical, and materials engineering programs of the department to 3rd and 4th year high school students. The Roadshow team was able to visit four schools as follows:   Philippine Science High School – Ilocos Region Campus (PSHS-Ilocos), Ilocos Sur National High School (ISNHS), Vigan<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_d8deba3dc7e74f3ca4e73bd80946d304.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/01/DMMME-Roadshow-Ilocos-Sur-Leg</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/01/DMMME-Roadshow-Ilocos-Sur-Leg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 05:25:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DOST-SEI Reaches Out to Remote Schools in Ilocos Sur</title><description><![CDATA[Bringing service to a whole new level, the Science Explorer and Push for Science teams of the Department of Science and Technology - Science Education Institute (DOST-SEI) went to Burgos and Banayoyo, Ilocos Sur last June 23–27, 2014. UP DMMME Asst. Prof. Myra Ruth Poblete served as one of the facilitators in the said event.   The Science Explorer Bus has been going to remote areas all over the Philippines to give alternative and interactive learning experiences to less fortunate students. In<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_4a9ac5655cf84758a76a14a833f97f4c.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/01/DOSTSEI-Reaches-Out-to-Remote-Schools-in-Ilocos-Sur</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/07/01/DOSTSEI-Reaches-Out-to-Remote-Schools-in-Ilocos-Sur</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 05:20:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Professor Emeritus Meliton Ordillas, Jr. is this year’s Most Distinguished Alumnus Awardee in Science and Technology</title><description><![CDATA[The University of the Philippines Alumni Association named DMMME’s Professor Emeritus Meliton Ordillas, Jr. as the Most Distinguished Alumnus Awardee in Science and Technology. The award is given to an individual who has demonstrated, in his/ her chosen field of endeavour, exceptional achievements and outstanding contributions that bring substantial benefits to society and distinct honor to the University [1].   Prof. Ordillas graduated Valedictorian in Zambales Rural High School (now Ramon<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_77cbbd21d3ef4e208ec0576d82da6979.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/Professor-Emeritus-Meliton-Ordillas-Jr-is-this-year%E2%80%99s-Most-Distinguished-Alumnus-Awardee-in-Science-and-Technology</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/Professor-Emeritus-Meliton-Ordillas-Jr-is-this-year%E2%80%99s-Most-Distinguished-Alumnus-Awardee-in-Science-and-Technology</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 06:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME’s Rubber Project Team Goes on Local Benchmarking Trip</title><description><![CDATA[DOST Rubber Project 3, headed by Dr. Leslie Joy Diaz, went on a benchmarking trip to various facilities handling natural rubber and potential rubber reinforcements in Mindanao from May 29 to June 2, 2014. This trip was conducted in order to gather knowledge about good industry and academic practices in the field of rubber, as well as potential sources for raw materials needed in rubber manufacture.   The Rubber Project Team is composed of Project Leader Dr. Leslie Joy Diaz, one Research<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_8e4710751c044f3d84c1ae7cdaf98ade.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/DMMME%E2%80%99s-Rubber-Project-Team-Goes-on-Local-Benchmarking-Trip</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/DMMME%E2%80%99s-Rubber-Project-Team-Goes-on-Local-Benchmarking-Trip</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 05:17:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Faculty and Graduate Students Attend Bio-based Polyols Seminar Workshop</title><description><![CDATA[A seminar-workshop on Bio-based Polyols and Polyurethanes was held at the Department of Chemistry of the Ateneo de Manila University last May 26-28, 2014. Four faculty members (Audric Zuriel Cruz, Jill Manapat, Myra Ruth Poblete, and Vincent Joseph Garcia) and two graduate students (Lorenz Anthony Fernando and Marianne Lorene Macailing) from DMMME participated in the said event.   The speaker of the seminar, Dr. Arnold A. Lubguban, gave a lecture about polyurethane foams including its]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/DMMME-Faculty-and-Graduate-Students-Attend-Biobased-Polyols-Seminar-Workshop</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/16/DMMME-Faculty-and-Graduate-Students-Attend-Biobased-Polyols-Seminar-Workshop</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 03:51:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Welcomes Freshmen and Their Parents with Orientation Program</title><description><![CDATA[DMMME welcomed a new batch of BS Mining Engineering (EM), BS Metallurgical Engineering (MetE) and BS Materials Engineering (MatE) freshmen for Academic Year 2014-2015 last May 8, 2014 with a Freshman Orientation for both incoming students and their parents.   The Freshman Orientation, held for incoming first-year students at the Engineering Theater, Melchor Hall, UP Diliman, strives to introduce students to the different programs of DMMME, as well as the curricula, retention rules and various<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_c00faf38c0a04a529d1784b081cfef14.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/04/DMMME-Welcomes-Freshmen-and-Their-Parents-with-Orientation-Program</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/04/DMMME-Welcomes-Freshmen-and-Their-Parents-with-Orientation-Program</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 08:44:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Congratulates Raymond Debuque: Asian Powerlifting Champion</title><description><![CDATA[Raymond Debuque, a metallurgical engineering student of U.P. Diliman, was among the Filipinos who made the country proud in the 2014 Asian Powerlifting Championships held last April 26-May 1 at the Great Eastern Hotel in Quezon City.   To quote from the Manila Times article [1]:   “Raymond Debuque and Edmund Cardano delivered four gold medals each in the tournament, which drew participants from Japan, Mongolia, Indonesia, South Korea, Hong Kong, United Arab Emirates, Oman, Taiwan and Uzbekistan.<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_04ff5aea406245d094037db9ccb97b44.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/04/DMMME-Congratulates-Raymond-Debuque-Asian-Powerlifting-Champion</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/06/04/DMMME-Congratulates-Raymond-Debuque-Asian-Powerlifting-Champion</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 05:55:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Participates in COE IGLAP Planning</title><description><![CDATA[Representatives from different institutes and departments of the UP College of Engineering underwent a two-day planning, workshop, and visit to Pacific Farms, Inc. (PFI), in Bolinao, Pangasinan last May 23-24, 2014 to set the roadmap for the Industry and Government Linkage with Academe Program (IGLAP) and the Student Internship Program.   Among the topics covered was the establishment of the Career Development Office (CDO), as well as the finalization of its scope and function. Moreover, the<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_cc94bb6453444a4db07232a541c77910.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/29/DMMME-Participates-in-COE-IGLAP-Planning</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/29/DMMME-Participates-in-COE-IGLAP-Planning</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 07:05:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Trains Five High School Students in Materials and Metallurgical Engineering</title><description><![CDATA[Five high school students from Philippine Science High School (PSHS) Bicol Region accomplished their Summer Science Internship Program (SSIP) by participating in various laboratory activities of DMMME from April 22 to May 19.   Three interns namely, Algregg Atibagos, Jan Edward Rocha, and Kenjie Earl Cea worked under the Composite Materials Laboratory while the other two, Mae Pursia Orbon and Ralph Revilla, Jr., worked under the Metallurgical Pilot Plant. The students were exposed to different<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_4c7805145bb94b4e89105c1bf0ff6b5e.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/24/DMMME-Trains-Five-High-School-Students-in-Materials-and-Metallurgical-Engineering</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/24/DMMME-Trains-Five-High-School-Students-in-Materials-and-Metallurgical-Engineering</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 06:22:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TEC 2014: Striving for Teaching Excellence</title><description><![CDATA[Forty-eight faculty members from UP Diliman underwent the bi-annual Teaching Effectiveness Course (TEC) organized by the UPD Office of the Director of Instruction (ODI) last May 12-16, 2014 at the School of Labor and Industrial Relations (SOLAIR). Six instructors from DMMME successfully finished the rigorous five-day training program, namely:   Baliong, Jasper (EM) Baladad, Karlo Leandro (MetE) Ejera, Stan Kristian (MetE) Gravador, Jordan David (MetE) Garcia, Vincent Joseph (MatE) Manapat, Jill<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_d954e2331f9441e8b157460211488e34.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/21/TEC-2014-Striving-for-Teaching-Excellence</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/21/TEC-2014-Striving-for-Teaching-Excellence</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 06:09:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dean Appoints New Department Chair</title><description><![CDATA[The new chairperson of UP DMMME, effective May 1, 2014, is Magdaleno R. Vasquez Jr., Dr.Eng.   Doc Jong, as he is called, graduated with a degree in BS Chemical Engineering from the University of the Philippines Diliman (UP Diliman) in 1997. He started his teaching career as a lecturer at the Department of Engineering Sciences of the same university before becoming an instructor (1999) and later on an assistant professor (2006). Doc Jong obtained his Master’s degree in Materials Science and]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/13/Dean-Appoints-New-Department-Chair</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/13/Dean-Appoints-New-Department-Chair</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 14:07:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Delegates from Different Agencies Benchmark in India on Rubber Research and Industry</title><description><![CDATA[A total of 31 delegates from the government, line agencies, Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao (ARMM), and academe visited Kerala and Mumbai, India last March 23-29, 2014 for a rubber benchmarking mission. The University of the Philippines Department of Mining, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering (UP DMMME) was represented by Dr. Leslie Joy L. Diaz.   The said activity aimed to provide the agencies an opportunity for exposure, as well as to learn from the experience and development<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_feb15ca01b3e4653b20e9f3fff31724c.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/05/Delegates-from-Different-Agencies-Benchmark-in-India-on-Rubber-Research-and-Industry</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/05/Delegates-from-Different-Agencies-Benchmark-in-India-on-Rubber-Research-and-Industry</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 03:39:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME to Attend ICMSE 2014</title><description><![CDATA[Assistant Professor Khryslyn G. Arano will be attending ICMSE 2014: International Conference on Materials Science and Engineering to present her research paper entitled Synthesis of Iron-modified Montmorillonite as Filler for Electrospun Nanocomposite Fibers. She will aslo be presenting another research output, which she co-authored with Prof. Michael Leo Dela Cruz, entitled A comparison of the Adsorption Mechanism of Arsenic on Iron-modified Nanoclay.   The said conference, which will be held]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/02/DMMME-to-Attend-ICMSE-2014</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/05/02/DMMME-to-Attend-ICMSE-2014</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 03:36:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DMMME Congratulates Batch 2014</title><description><![CDATA[A total of 94 candidates from the department joined the rest of the College of Engineering graduates last April 28, 2014 at the UP Diliman amphitheater. The Mining Engineering program had its first summa cum laude graduate. Also from the three bachelor’s degree programs of the department, 5 candidates graduated with magna cum laude and 6 with cum laude honors. We wish our graduates more successes in the future!   BS Mining Engineering ALBERTO, Krizia Ann Pelejo AMORIN, Carlo de Luna CASTRO,]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/04/30/DMMME-Congratulates-Batch-2014</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2014/04/30/DMMME-Congratulates-Batch-2014</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fluor Daniel Inc. Forges Link with Academe: Lecture Room Inaugurated</title><description><![CDATA[The new 60-seater, state-of-the art, fully-furnished lecture room, finished through the support of Fluor Daniel, Inc. Philippines (Fluor), was inaugurated last May 9, 2013 at the Department of Mining, Metallurgical, and Materials Engineering (DMMME). The ceremony was graced by Fluor Vice President and Country Manager for Operations Dan Spinks, UP College of Engineering Dean Aura C. Matias, and UP Engineering Research and Development Foundation, Inc. Board Member Alfonso Aliga, Jr. The Fluor<img src="http://static.parastorage.com/media/e0b8ad_091ae40f553945a69287ee1c73fde537.jpg_256"/>]]></description><link>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2013/05/30/Fluor-Daniel-Inc-Forges-Link-with-Academe-Lecture-Room-Inaugurated</link><guid>http://www.dmmme.coe.upd.edu.ph/single-post/2013/05/30/Fluor-Daniel-Inc-Forges-Link-with-Academe-Lecture-Room-Inaugurated</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>